Guide to the Marcel-Louis Baugniet Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marcel-Louis Baugniet collection
1922-1936
GEN MSS 900
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.33
(2 boxes)
The collection includes material designed by Baugniet including original drawings for advertisements and other ephemera, printed versions of advertisements and sheet music, posters and ephemera related to Baugniet's exhibitions, and a periodical featuring an article on his wife Akarova.
Baugniet, Marcel-Louis, 1896-1995
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael R. Weintraub, Inc., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Marcel-Louis Baugniet (1896-1995)
Marcel-Louis Baugniet was a Belgian painter, graphic artist, stage designer, and furniture designer. He was also one of the principal promoters of the Constructivist style and after his return from Paris in 1922, with the work of the French and Russian avant-garde fresh in his mind, he was determined to rouse Belgium from its artistic torpor and create a new utopian world of functional, elegant and rational form. When the Constructivists fell out of favor with the critics and the public he turned his attention to interiors and furniture design, and only at the end of his life were his earlier Constructivist paintings rediscovered, exhibited, and celebrated. His early career was heavily influenced by his companion and wife of six years, the avant-garde dancer Akarova (Marguerite Acarin). For her, he produced costumes and stage designs, and inspired by her he created his finest work of graphic art: the series of woodcuts entitled Kaloprosopies. One of his early projects on his return to Belgium was to reform the backward and undistinguished tradition of Belgian advertising and graphic arts. To that end, in 1922 he founded the advertising firm Fulgura, whose style was heavily influenced by contemporary Dutch and Russian posters with their bold and simple lines.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes material designed by Baugniet including original drawings for advertisements and other ephemera, printed versions of advertisements and sheet music, posters and ephemera related to Baugniet's exhibitions, and a periodical featuring an article on his wife Akarova.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Graphic Designs, 1922-1930. II. Exhibition Ephemera, 1925-1929. III. Other Material, 1936.
Constructivism (Art) -- Belgium; Constructivism (Art) -- Belgium -- Exhibitions; Design drawings -- Belgium; Graphic artists -- Belgium; Graphic arts -- Belgium; Painting, Belgian -- 20th Century -- Exhibitions; Songs with piano; Belgium -- Graphic arts -- 20th Century; Advertisements -- Belgium -- 20th Century; Ephemera (general object genre) -- Belgium -- 20th Century; Posters -- Belgium -- 20th Century; Graphic artists -- Belgium -- 20th Century; Akarova, 1904-; Baugniet, Marcel-Louis, 1896-1995
- Graphic Designs, 1922-1930; Series I; 24
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains original artwork and printed versions of designs by Baugniet.
  - Arlita. Chanson Lumineuse, by J. A. Van de Vyver (Bruxelles: 1925?) (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 1)
    General note
    Sheet music from the period when Baugniet was developing designs for Phillips. The song is dedicated to the Phillips electric lamp, and the woman on the cover is a stylized vision of Akarova
  - Art et lndustrie, no.1; gouache and ink on paper, 1926 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    Design for cover
  - Ateliers Fulgura envelopes; printed version, circa 1922 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Stationery for Baugniet's design studio.
  - Centre d'Information de la Couleur en Belgique; gouache, ink, and graphite on paper, annotated in ballpoint pen, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Électrolux S. A. advertisement; printed version, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Advertising postcard for Lux vacuum cleaners, by Publicité Fulgura
  - L'Escrime. 20 images de Marcel Baugniet; printed version., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Small format advertisement for a book of images by Baugniet, who was an avid fencer.
  - Fortiter ephemera; printed versions, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Business card, small advertisement, and stationery for Fortiter, a manufacturer of modern embroideries and an interior design firm
  - La Galerie de "Spectacles," Bruxelles, du 26 Septembre au 10 Octobre 1925; printed version, 8 p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Cover typography by Baugniet. A rare catalogue of an exhibition of Belgian stage design held from September 26 to October 10, 1925, that was incorporated into Frederick Kiesler's International Theater exhibition of 1926.
  - Gem Polisch; gouache on paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Advertisement for automobile polish made in Belgium
  - Giso brochure and trade catalogue no. 26; printed versions, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Advertising for light fixture manufacturer
  - L'Interieur Moderne advertising card; printed version, circa 1929 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Advertisement for the design company created by Baugniet and Ewaud van Tonderen in 1927. Verso features a photograph of a domestic bar designed by Baugniet.
  - Jam hosiery advertisements; gouache and ink on paper, with two printed versions of each design, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Advertisements for "Le Bas Jam" stockings for women and "La Chausette Jam" socks for men, both the dream of elegance
  - Maryse Couture Fourrures; ink on paper, with printed version, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Advertisement for a Brussels furrier
  - Premier cleaner électrique advertisement; printed version, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Advertising card for vacuum cleaners, by Publicité Fulgura
  - Quelques Mises au Point de l'Art Contemporain; printed broadside, 1927 Aug (Box 1, Folder 15)
    A manifesto by Baugniet and Ewaud van Tonderen listing eight truths including: the useful is beautiful; form follows function; and we celebrate the beauty of the machine.
  - Speedford BB Motors advertising card; printed version, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Theatre de l'Equipe Ste. Coop.; gouache, ink, and graphite on card, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Theatre de Marais, soiree de gala; gouache, ink, and graphite on paper, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Cover of a program featuring a performance by Akarova in 1926.
  - Trois Quatrains pour ma Mie, by René Bernier (Bruxelles: Fernand Lauweryns Editeur, 1927) (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
    Sheet music with Constructivist cover by Baugniet.
  - Weiler Biscuits et Desserts, Bruxelles, advertisement; printed version, undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 20)
  - Untitled illustration of child with pull-toy in garden; printed version, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Exhibition Ephemera, 1925-1929; Series II; 3
  Arranged chronologically.
  The series contains two posters and one exhibition catalogue documenting exhibits of Baugniet's work.
  - La Lanterne Sourde Presente des Peintres Constructeurs. M. L. Baugniet, P. Flouquet, J. J. Gaillard, Jasinska, V. Servranckx, Xhrouet. Du 14 au 29 Novembre. (Bruxelles: Cabinet Maldoror, 1925) (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 22)
    Poster for an exhibition of the Belgian Constructivists organized by Pierre Bourgeois.
  - L'Exposition M.L. Baugniet, Palais des Beaux Arts. Bruxelles 9-20 Fevrier, 1929 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 23)
    Poster for Baugniet's first solo exhibition.
  - Exposition M L Baugniet. Palais des Beaux-Arts Bruxelles du 9 au Fév. 1929; 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    With Constructivist cover designed by Baugniet, one reproduction, and a list of 22 paintings.
- Other Material, 1936; Series III
  The series contains one periodical.
  - Les Femmes dans L'Action Mondiale, 4 Mars 1936 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 25)
    Magazine with a cover photograph of Akarova and an article by C. Godefroid entitled "Akarova et son Art."